Guide to the Ezra Cornell Papers, 1746-1888
Cornell, Ezra Papers, 1746-1888
- Series I. Correspondence 1746-1878
  - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1828-1845
      - May 13, 1844 - August 9, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        n.d. Morse's telegraphic alphabet and phrases written by Samuel F.B. Morse for use of Ezra Cornell on test line between Washington, D.C. and Baltimore.
        July 28, 1844. and children describing in detail his journey by coach to Syracuse and train to Albany, his impressions of the State Geological collection, and discussing family businesses, finance, and poles for Benjamin Wood.
        July 29, 1844. and children describing his trip by steamer "Portsmouth" down the Hudson as far as town of Hudson.
        July 29, 1844. Samuel F.B. Morse to Ezra Cornell from New York:
        "Things in relation to the Telegraph look well, and if our plans succeed here, you will not want for ample employment."
        August 9, 1844. and children concerning interest in the telegraph from companies in Boston, Philadelphia, and New York; potential employment with telegraph for family members; continued description of trip down the Hudson, including discussion of the raising of a sunken ship rumored to be that of Capt. Kidd.
        Ithaca; Washington, D.C.; Baltimore; Albany, N.Y.
        Morse, Samuel F.B.; Wood, Benjamin; Burbank, David; Vail, Alfred; Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - August 10, 1844 - September 25, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Family correspondence; Ithaca politics; Whigs; Loco Focos; plows; telegraph business correspondence; telegraph exhibition.
        August 18, 1844. and children reflecting on slavery and national politics:
        "My dear, I am convinced that our 'humble cot' is the dwelling place of more happiness in one day than falls to the lot of many a human being in this portion of our boasted 'land of Liberty' during a long life.
        "Slavery as it is garenteed in the states by the Constitution is bad enough and must be indured until it is removed by the fource of enlightened publick opinion acting upon the slaveholder, but for the sake of humanity let it not be extended."
        September 2, 1844. and children discussing the bustle (women's fashion) and giving detailed directions to Mary Ann concerning her trip to Washington, D.C.
        Baltimore; Ithaca; Washington, D.C.; Boston.
        Burbank, David; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Lincoln, A.B.; Slater, Justus; Wood, O.S.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Smith, F.O.J.
      - October 7, 1844 - November 22, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Family correspondence; business correspondence; telegraph exhibition in Boston; telegraph; elections; "lightning."
        November 24, 1844. quoting "A World of Love at Home," a poem by J.J. Reynolds and giving instructions to his children on how to maintain this at home.
        Boston; Ithaca.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Wood, O.S.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Vail, Alfred.
      - December 1, 1844 - December 29, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Business correspondence; Family correspondence; telegraph; telegraph exhibition in Boston; electric conductors; alarm machine; chess games over the telegraph.
        December 3, 1844. Samuel F.B. Morse to Ezra Cornell discussing the claims of Dr. Charles T. Jackson that Jackson was the inventor of the telegraph.
        December 5, 1844. Orrin S. Wood to Ezra Cornell discussing use of telegraph to report proceedings of Congress.
        December 15, 1844. and children:
        "I had heard while at Providence last Thursday that Mary had recd. proposals from Robert Macy but had decided not to accept them, I was glad to hear of that determination as I detest the practice of cousins marrying or any marriage between persons in which there can be traced the most distant relationship. I go for the improvement instead of the deterioration of our race?"
        Alarm machine, telegraph for the Postmaster.
        December 22, 1844. and children sending New Years wishes and messages to Mary Ann, Alonzo, Frank, Elizabeth, and Oliver Perry to accompany books for each of them.
        Boston; New York City.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Speed, J.J.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Smith, F.O.J.; Wood, O.S.
      - January 2, 1845 - January 31, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: line from New York to Boston, materials and supplies, line damaged in storm, New York telegraph exhibition; discussion of possible duel between Congressmen Clingman and Yancey; conflict with Beebe.
        January 15, 1845. E.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell regarding E.B.'s financial difficulties and hopes for assistance from Ezra Cornell.
        January 29, 1845. Jeremiah S. Beebe to Ezra Cornell:
        "I think it was 1829 or 30 that I applied to Otis Eddy for a man to mend my plaster mill, and he recommended you. At that time I was worth $40.000 and you perhaps 40/, soon after I employed you to take charge of my affair at Fall Creek. From that time forward for at least 8 or 9 years you was in my employment at a good salary. You had my means to live on and my [?] to try your crazy experiments upon, and what is the result. I am now obliged to wear the old clothes about that I had 7 years ago and you are moving upon lightening. You have been brought forward to the world's notice?"
        New York City; Washington, D.C.
        Wood, O.S.; Smith, F.O.J.; Nash, John; Burbank, David; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - February 1, 1845 - March 23, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Wool factory (Ithaca); alarm machine; telegraph business correspondence: New York telegraph exhibition, Congressional appropriation, plans for telegraphic enterprise; hoop machine; conflict with Beebe; fire at National Theater in Washington; Ithaca fire; E.B. proposes fresh water business in Chicago.
        New York City; Ithaca; Washington, D.C.
        Burbank, David; Avery, Thomas; Speed, J.J.; Wood, O.S.; Smith, F.O.J.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Cornell, E.B.
      - April 10, 1845 - May 29, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: line maintenance, materials and supplies; plow business.
        April 19, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Samuel F.B. Morse:
        "?my object was to aid in carrying through, what I regarded as a magnificent experiment, and laying a foundation for future profitable employment."
        Telegraph conflicts, alarm machine.
        May 29, 1845. Amos Kendall to Ezra Cornell:
        "?we are willing to arrange for your employment and services in behalf of the Magnetic Telegraph Company of which you are already a member with this understanding?"
        Morse, Samuel F.B.; Smith, F.O.J.; Burbank, David; Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Kendall, Amos; Lincoln, A.B.
      - June 15, 1845 - June 28, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: rights of way, construction, materials and supplies.
        June 22, 1845. and children describing stage coach journey:
        "The night got rather cool and a great coat would have been comfortable but I did not suffer at all for the want of one and I'm inclined to the opinion that the absence of the warmth from an overcoat was all that saved me from stage sickness if so the circumstance may be given as another evidence that 'poverty is a blessing.'
        "The children must not be idle, they must study some, work some, and play some, they must be at something all the time."
        Health, possible routes out of the city for the telegraph, visit to old neighborhood (Bergen county), Staten Island.
        June 30, 1845. and children concerning the approaching Fourth of July:
        "?the only guarantee the present generation has that our free and hapy form of government will be handed down unimpaired as it came from the hands of our Patriot Fathers, to our children and our children's children is in universal education?Then let Universal Education be the Patriot's wachword?"
        New York City.
        Kendall, Amos; Cornell, Mary Ann; Smith, F.O.J.; Burbank, David.
      - July 6, 1845 - July 31, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence: routes in New York City and New Jersey, and New York to Philadelphia, materials and supplies, stock subscriptions.
        July 11, 1845. and children:
        "I think Elizabeth is quite romantic to call her Father's letters novels'?but she will find this difference between the two, novels are the coinage of missguided brains, making no instructions to truth or reality, but dealing largely in 'the fancies' while her Father's letters contain truth, plain unvarnished truth, and I hope that is the quality that induces E. to admire them."
        On visiting the Old Stone School House where he had gone to school 27 years ago:
        "Not being satisfied that I got the worth of the money that my good Father paid for my larning there, I sought to indemnify myself by obtaining some relic of the house itself so I knocked some pieces out of it's 'time honoured walls' which I shall deposit properly labilled in my museum of curiosities."
        July 27, 1845. and children written to
        "appear like a Novel to my little Rosebud."
        New York City; Ithaca.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Smith, F.O.J.; Kendall, Amos; Cornell, E.B.; O'Reilly, Henry.
      - August 2, 1845 - September 30, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: Utica line, instruments, materials and supplies, river crossing, insulation for wires, magnets; Steamship Great Britain; Family correspondence.
        August 10, 1845. and children:
        "?I must pay you the compliment of being quite a financier?you must keep a keen eye on your tenants and make them 'Pony up' -- does not Potter trade in something that you want if so try to get something out of him, take candy if you can get nothing else, Perry would soon learn to eat candy if he dont already know how?"
        August 17, 1845. and children discussing health and fruit, and improvements to telegraph instruments:
        "I am making other improvements that I have full confidence will be successful by business superintending my work getting materials, planning and draughting for new improvements writing my letters and accts. keeps me fully employed I don't get half the time to read that I should like to devote to it, things look well and will come out right in the end."
        September 19, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann and children describing telegraph exhibit at State Fair in Utica:
        "I had about 2000 visiters a room 30 by 40 crowded from morning till night. The wonder with all was how I stood it, to talk so much and so long as I did in explaining the telegraph to such a multitude."
        New York City; Utica, N.Y.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Butterfield, John; Messenger, S.; Kendall, Amos; Cornell, E.B.; Vail, Alfred; Rogers, H.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.
      - October 1, 1845 - October 16, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical issues, instruments, materials and supplies, routes; Family correspondence.
        October 5, 1845. and children:
        "?my old hat crown was most out, and a hole in my pants and some buttons off and my shoes riped down the side, but that is nothing my heart is sound and my head clear?"
        October 15, 1845. Ezra Cornell to C.G. Page, discussing improvements in instrumentand magnet designs:
        "I am unconcious of having done anything wrong in the matter, and am very sorry if you have the impression that I would wrong you in the slightest degree, even were it in my power, I have done nothing and would do nothing that I should not be willing that you should do by me, I act from principle founded upon justice to all men."
        Utica; New York City.
        Faxton, Theodore; Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Wood, O.S.; Kendall, Amos; Butterfield, John; Page, C.G.
      - October 18, 1845 - October 31, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: patent rights, instruments, New York, Albany & Buffalo line, materials and supplies, construction of lines, finances; Ithaca schools.
        October 30, 1845. and children:
        "Your going to church I approve as I do your doings in general, I think however the churches are not as usefull as they would be if they would teach their diciples?to practice upon the precepts laid down by Christ. Do unto others, as you would that should do unto you, Love your neighbour as your self, Let him who is free from sin cast the first stone, &c &c &c."
        Bible quotations (proverbs) concerning husbands and wives.
        Page, C.G.; Wells, Henry; Wood, O.S.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Kendall, Amos.
      - November 1, 1845 - November 9, 1845 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Telegraph business correspondence: instruments, materials and supplies, technical issues, patent rights, Buffalo to Lockport line in operation; Family correspondence; Fall Creek tunnel.
        November 6, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "If you go to Dryden, you and Otis and Norman and perhaps one or two other young philosophers might get up a Philosophical Club, and spend your winter evenings profitably?
        ?the serenade at Unkle Js must have been interesting. Dryden is a great place for musick, but such musicians make poor phylosiphers. I had rather you would study phylosiphy than musick in that school."
        November 5, 1845. Ezra Cornell to E.B. Cornell:
        "I can't at the present time tell when I shall be at home, nor where I shall spend the winter. The Phil. Co. wants me to stay and keep the charge of working their line. The New York, Albany & Buffalo Co. want me, and offer $2000 for me to take charge of their line and the N.Y. and Boston Co. want me to take theirs, and will do as well by me as either, and I don't know yet which will get me. I want to go where I can be of the most service to the general enterprise."
        November 12, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "?I am not shure but I shall contrive some way by which I could kiss you by telegraph. How would you like to be bussed by lightning? It would seem odd no doubt, but there is no telling what will be done yet, these are the times of strange and marvelous things?"
        Wood, O.S.; Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Monroe, C.
      - November 10, 1845 - November 20, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence: electricity; new lines (Lockport and Buffalo, Washington and Philadelphia).
        Ithaca; Lockport, N.Y.; Washington, D.C.
        Renwick, James; Cornell, E.B.; Kendall, Amos; Wood, O.S.; Smith, F.O.J.; Sage, H.W.
      - November 22, 1845 - November 30, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence; Family correspondence.
        November 23, 1845. Ezra Cornell:
        "My section of the Tel extends to Somerville New Jersey about 70 miles by the rout of the wires."
        November 30, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "I want you to be diligent in your studies, for you will soon be wanted for something else. I am going to have a telegraph from Ithaca to Auburn and you may be wanted to take one of the stations. So you see it is important that you should improve the time well, while you have a chance to go to school."
        Ithaca; Lockport; Washington, D.C.; New York City.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Kendall, Amos; Smith, F.O.J.; Wells, Henry
      - December 2, 1845 - December 13, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, patent rights.
        December 7, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "The duty of the mother outweigh the affections of the wife, that is a heavenly emplanted virtue in the breast of woman.
        I am bound to make a thousand dollars out of that operation [Ithaca to Auburn telegraph] but this I say to you in confidence and don't want it to go further at present."
        O'Reilly, Henry; Faxton, Theodore; Kendall, Amos; Carter, Samuel P.; Goell, A.C.; Eddy, James; Smith, F.O.J.; Wood, O.S.
      - December 14, 1845 - December 22, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, finances, materials and supplies; Family correspondence.
        December 14, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "There is nothing I have to reflect on that gives me more satisfaction than the fact that my life is insured for the benefit of my Dear Wife and children."
        Kendall, Amos; Goell, A.C.; Wood, O.S.; Butterfield, J.; Smith, F.O.J.; Eddy, James; O'Reilly, Henry.
      - December 24, 1845 - December 31, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, conflict with Vail and others, question of Ezra Cornell's employment, stock subscriptions offered to Ithaca businessmen.
        December 30, 1845. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "I thank you for your wish of a 'merry Christmas' and can inform you that I made it merry with work."
        O'Reilly, Henry; Wood, O.S.; Vail, Alfred; Kendall, Amos; Faxton, Theodore.
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1846-1847
      - January 1, 1846 - January 24, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, patent rights, stock subscriptions.
        January 10, 1846. Samuel F.B. Morse to Ezra Cornell:
        "At 12 o'clock on Monday and the same on Tuesday at 10 o'clock?you will strike the letter F *--* *--* in the same way from Fort Lee to Philadelphia and also to N York."
        Kendall, Amos; Smith, F.O.J.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Wood, O. S.; Mooers, Henry.
      - January 27, 1846 - February 23, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, personal conflict, establishment of new lines, stock subscriptions in Ithaca.
        February 8, 1846. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell admonishing him for revealing elements of slothful behavior.
        February 9, 1846. Ezra Cornell to the Editor of the Herald concerning disputed invention of the telegraph.
        February 22, 1846. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell calculating in real dollars the lifetime costs of drinking alcohol and using tobacco:
        "I am very glad that the temperance reform has reached Fall Creek."
        Eddy, James; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Wood, O.S.; Atwell, Winthrop; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Faxton, Theodore.
      - February 24, 1846 - March 18, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, Ithaca subscribers; "Cornelia"; temperance movement in Ithaca; letters to Alonzo with advice and counsel on education and responsible living.
        March 1, 1846. Description of telegraph lines and bridges.
        New York City; Ithaca; Boston.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Atwell, Winthrop; Eddy, James; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Carter, Samuel P.; Cornell, E.B.; Faxton, Theodore; Livingston, Charles.
      - March 20, 1846 - March 30, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, Ithaca stock subscriptions.
        March 30, 1846. E.B. Cornell from Ithaca:
        "We are now enjoying the Blessings and comforts of revivle of religion in Ithaca - the reverend Mr. John Moffett is here Delivering a Course of lectures on American Literature & pouring forth his Eloquent Irish Soul in the Pulpit every other Evening the Cthouse was cramed full to overflowing yesterday."
        Boston; New York City; Utica; Ithaca.
        Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, Franklin C.; Wood, O.S.; Eddy, James; Park, J.D.; Cornell, E.B.; Smith, F.O.J.
      - April 1, 1846 - April 29, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines.
        April 29, 1846. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "I left the city of NY last eve With the floating Palace Hendrick Hudson. I brought up with me half a dozen flowering trees. I think you had better set them in your nice little dooryard."
        Boston; New York City; Albany; Utica.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Carter, Samuel P.; Wood, O.S.; Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - May 1, 1846 - May 12, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, materials and supplies, establishment of new lines.
        New York City; Utica.
        Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, E.B.
      - May 15, 1846 - May 31, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, materials and supplies; Beebe importunes Ezra Cornell for money.
        Ithaca; New York City.
        Faxton, Theodore; Eddy, James; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Cornell, E.S.
      - June 3, 1846 - June 16, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, materials and supplies, finances, establishment of new lines.
        Albany; Boston; New York City.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Faxton, Theodore.
      - June 17, 1846 - June 29, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        New York City; Poughkeepsie, N.Y.; Ithaca; Aurora, N.Y.
        Cornell, E.B.; Kendall, Amos; Cornell, E.B.; Smith, F.O.J.; Eddy, James.
      - July 1, 1846 - July 9, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        New York City; Albany.
        Eddy, James; Wood, O.S.; Cornell, E.B.
      - July 10, 1846 - July 21, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        New York City; Poughkeepsie.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, E.B.; Livingston and Wells.
      - July 25, 1846 - August 4, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        August 3, 1846. F.A. Brown to Ezra Cornell:
        "I regret to hear Smith is not more successful than he is on the Boston line. Poor fellow, I am sorry for him, those loafers on the Philadelphia line will now be able to exult over his adversity."
        New York City; Ithaca; Buffalo.
        King, George W.; Wood, O.S.; Bristol, John S.; Cornell, E.B.; Faxton, Theodore.
      - August 7, 1846 - August 31, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, stock subscriptions, E.B. Cornell seeks employment, contention with Faxton about the Albany line.
        August 31, 1846. F.O.J. Smith to Ezra Cornell:
        "I am sorry to learn from various sources of your having frequently made me the subject of much unfavorable conjecture and remark with men in my employ, as well as with others, in connexion with a female with whome you boarded in New York. Now I ask no man to become the keper of my morals or character?"
        Faxton, Theodore; Eddy, James; Wood, Benjamin; Cornell, E.B.; Brown, F.A.; Wood, Phebe; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Smith, F.O.J.
      - September 6, 1846 - October 9, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, proposed line between Washington, D.C. and New Orleans, price per transmission.
        October 7, 1846. Incidence of vandalism of the New York line.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Eddy, James; Bullock, A.B.
      - October 11, 1846 - October 17, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, proposals for establishment of new lines, finances.
        October 15, 1846. Telegraph stock, shares, dividends.
        Ithaca; Hudson, N.Y.
        Brown, F.A.; Kendall, Amos; Bullock, A.B.; Cornell, E.B.; Eddy, James.
      - October 18, 1846 - October 30, 1846 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: technical matters, establishment of new lines, complication of communication among stations in New York State.
        October 20, 1846. Negotiation of stock transfers (Ithaca Telegraph Company).